<title>Updated software and resources</title>
<link>http://jnpopgen.org/2014/01/12/updated-software-and-resources/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2014 21:47:18 +0000</pubDate>
<dc:creator>jno5</dc:creator>
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://jnpopgen.org/?p=153</guid>
<description></description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[A few maintenance items:
<ul>
<li>I have just moved the ENCprime software over to github and updated <a href="https://github.com/jnovembre/ENCprime">the link</a> on the software/resources page.  This small piece of software computes a measure of codon usage bias for FASTA formatted sequences.</li>
<li>I also added to the software/resources <a href="https://github.com/jnovembre/Novembre_etal_2008_misc">a link</a> to a github repository with several files that help reproduce the main figure of the Novembre et al (2008) paper as from time to time I get requests for some help along those lines.</li>
</ul>
And in lab news, there have been some nice developments:
<ul>
<li>Our team's paper on inferring migration origins of birds using genetics and isotopes <a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/resolve/openurl?genre=article&amp;sid=nlm:pubmed&amp;issn=0962-1083&amp;date=2013&amp;volume=22&amp;issue=16&amp;spage=4163">came out in Molecular Ecology</a> in the latter half of last year.  Colin Rundel did excellent work on this project as part of his dissertation, and Kristen Ruegg and colleagues are doing awesome follow-up work on this project that will be exciting to share.  Molecular Ecology ran a <a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/mec.12441/full">News and Views piece</a> on the work by Thor Veen.</li>
<li>PhD student Eunjung Han's paper on assessing the impact of low coverage sequencing on population genetic inference has <a href="http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=24288159">come out in Molecular Biology and Evolution</a>.</li>
<li>PhD student Darren Kessner's software for forward simulation of selection on quantitative traits (<a href="https://bitbucket.org/dkessner/forqs">forqs</a>) is now described formally with <a href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/content/early/2013/12/27/bioinformatics.btt712.long">a software note published in Bioinformatics</a>.</li>
<li>The <a href="http://www.genetics.ucla.edu/software/admixture/">ADMIXTURE software</a> developed by David Alexander (now at Pac Bio) recently had its 200th citation.</li>
<li>A collaborative paper led by Sebastian Zollner's group at University of Michigan, and recent PhD Matt Zawistowski in particular, has now been published in EJHG.  The paper is titled "<a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24398795">Analysis of rare variant population structure in Europeans explains differential stratification of gene-based tests</a>" and it has very interesting results on how many of the novel gene-based tests perform in stratified mapping samples.</li>


<title>Wolf/dog genomes paper out</title>
<link>http://jnpopgen.org/2014/01/20/wolfdog-genomes-paper-out/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2014 21:48:02 +0000</pubDate>
<dc:creator>jno5</dc:creator>
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://jnpopgen.org/?p=161</guid>
<description></description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[&nbsp;

This last week we had our work on using wolf and dog genomes to understand dog domestication go to press!

<span style="line-height:1.714285714;font-size:1rem;">Here's a set of the relevant links to read more in depth:</span>
<ol>
<li><a href="http://www.plosgenetics.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pgen.1004016;jsessionid=74FB84F5F2972AB43BDA3677EFA17580">The main paper in PLoS Genetics.</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.plosgenetics.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pgen.1004093">A nice paired perspective piece "How much is that in dog years" in PLoS Genetics from Greger Larson and Dan Brady.</a></li>
<li><a href="http://haldanessieve.org/2014/01/17/author-post-genome-sequencing-highlights-the-dynamic-early-history-of-dogs/">A great post from Ilan Gronau on how the multiple methods we used helped illuminate an overall picture of dog domestication.</a></li>
</ol>
And a big thanks to all the great researchers who contributed to this project, especially my former postdoc Adam Freedman who was first author on the project and colleague Robert Wayne who was the co-senior author with me.


<title>More on dogs and wolves...</title>
<link>http://jnpopgen.org/2014/02/05/more-on-dogs-and-wolves/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2014 18:52:31 +0000</pubDate>
<dc:creator>jno5</dc:creator>
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://jnpopgen.org/?p=181</guid>
<description></description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[The good news:  Our recent paper on dog domestication has been recommended by <a href="http://f1000.com/prime/718248234?bd=1">F1000</a>. Thanks to F1000 member Norman Johnson for taking note of our work!

The bad news:  Our paper was misinterpreted and misused by Ham during the Nye/Ham debate regarding creationism and evolution.  There are many angles on which one could respond, but I want to quickly reinforce:  We clearly see dogs are a close relative of wolves on the basis of DNA sequence similarity.  Everything we observe is consistent with a history of descent with modification and the very same figure he cited shows how dogs fit into an evolutionary tree with related lineages of wolves and a golden jackal.

More generally speaking as a geneticist: Numerous subtle predictions of evolutionary theory are borne out in DNA sequence data. As genome-scale sequences have finally become available to us, it's been amazing to see how a single theoretical framework can predict so many patterns seen in these massive datasets.  It would be impossible to make sense of our observations without it.  In more practical terms, numerous advances in the understanding and treatment of heritable and infectious diseases, as well as in conservation biology, would not have been possible without an evolutionary framework for analysis and interpretation of data.

To read more, writer Stephanie Pappas has an article summarizing immediate scientific responses to the debate.  Find it <a href="http://www.livescience.com/43127-nye-creationism-debate-response.html">here</a>.]]></content:encoded>


<title>Lab News: Summer 2014</title>
<link>http://jnpopgen.org/2014/07/23/lab-news-summer-2014/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2014 17:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
<dc:creator>jno5</dc:creator>
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://jnpopgen.org/?p=241</guid>
<description></description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[We've been having lots of fun lately in the lab.  Some recent highlights are (in a rough reverse chronological order):
<ul>
<li>We hosted the first Midwest Popgen Group meeting with the help of the great staff and students/postdocs here at U of C and organizing committee with Sebastian Zollner (U Michigan), Don Conrad (Wash-U), and Bret Payseur (U Wisc-Madison). We had approximately 80 attendees, from 20 different off-campus labs and 17 on-campus labs. Attendees drove in from Illinois, Michigan, Indiana, Missouri, Wisconsin, and Minnesota. There were 11 talks total, with 7 by grad-students/postdocs and 4 by assistant professors, and 15 posters.  We had a great set of talks and then a fun BBQ at the Point.  Mo Siddiq is preparing a website with photos from the event.  (7/19)</li>
<li>We have released a new teaching/research tool.  <a href="http://popgen.uchicago.edu/ggv">The Geography of Genetic Variants browser</a>.  This is the hard work of our "programmer-at-large" Joe Marcus.  It's also a pilot project for a grant we submitted earlier this summer to work on challenges that arise visualizing population structure in genomic-scale variation data.  (7/15)</li>
<li>A <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2014/07/14/friends-genetics-study_n_5585228.html">Huffington Post article</a> quotes me raising doubts about a recent PNAS paper on how genetics influence friend pairings (7/14)</li>
<li>Joel Smith and Hussein Al-asadi successfully defended their thesis proposals!</li>
<li>Genetics recently published an <a href="http://www.genetics.org/content/197/3/809.full">invited short perspective piece</a> on the new fastSTRUCTURE paper in which I give an overview of work on the model behind STRUCTURE and its subsequent variants.  (7/1)</li>
<li>We have enjoyed some great summer conferences including the SMBE meeting in Puerto Rico back in June and a meeting with our SardiNIA project collaborators in Ann Arbor, Michigan earlier in July.</li>
<li>Darren Kessner and Eunjung Han submitted their final chapters for publication and successfully defended their PhDs!  Darren is off to a fantastic job at the elite Marlborough School in Los Angeles where he will be teaching math and expanding the computer science curriculum.   Eunjung (a.k.a. Christine) is now joining the excellent team at AncestryDNA developing tools for interfacing genealogical and genetic data. We had a big party in LA to celebrate their achievement and are wishing them the best as they move onwards in their new adventures!</li>
